<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-03-15T21:19:16+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">A bit about Interpretability</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/03/15/interpret.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A bit about Interpretability" /><published>2025-03-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/03/15/interpret</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/03/15/interpret.html"><![CDATA[<p><a id="chapter1"></a>
Interpretability in machine learning is one of the topics I paid attention to throughout my PhD. Especially in biomedical research, building models that predict outcomes accurately is thrilling, but it’s not the entire story. The magic happens when we truly understand what these models tell us and translate those insights into something meaningful. In this post, let’s dive into why interpretability matters and explore some practical ways to make our models both understandable and impactful.</p>

<h3 id="1-interpretability-in-biomedical-research">1. Interpretability in Biomedical research</h3>
<p><a id="chapter2"></a>
Interpretability isn’t just a fancy word—it’s crucial for translating ML models into real-world biomedical applications. It helps scientists uncover biomarkers, provides deeper mechanistic insights into diseases, and assists biotech and pharma in drug discovery. Equally important, interpretability boosts trust: doctors, researchers, and even patients can better accept and use ML tools when they understand what’s behind predictions.</p>

<p>Simpler models often provide better interpretability. For instance, let’s take a look at this cute picture comparing a decision tree and a deep neural network:</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/assets/images/interpretability.jpeg" alt="Figure 1" style="max-width: 70%; height: auto;" />
  <p style="max-width: 80%; margin: auto; font-size: 10px;"><strong>Comparison between decision tree and deep neural network.</strong></p> 
</div>

<p>In the decision tree, we see exactly how decisions are made (e.g., age and gender directly influence the risk, and age is relatively more important). It’s as clear as preparing an organic fruit salad—you see exactly what’s going in, fresh and straightforward! Conversely, the deep neural network is more like a premade smoothie—delicious but with mysterious ingredients blended together, leaving you guessing what’s inside!</p>

<h3 id="2-inherently-interpretable-algorithms">2. Inherently interpretable algorithms</h3>
<p><a id="chapter3"></a>
In biomedical research, we often prefer simpler models such as linear regression, logistic regression, or decision trees. Why? Because most biomedical studies typically have smaller sample sizes and limited computational resources. Besides, simpler models generally perform reasonably well for tasks like classification and forecasting.</p>

<p>These simpler models come with inherent interpretability, meaning you can directly extract feature importance from the model parameters themselves. For example:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Linear models</strong>: The coefficients directly indicate the importance and direction (positive or negative influence) of each feature. Like picking out individual fruits, you clearly see what and how much contributes to your tasty salad.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Tree-based models</strong> (Decision Trees, Random Forests): You can explicitly visualize and interpret how each feature influences predictions through tree splits. Feature importance can be quantified by how much each feature reduces uncertainty or error—each decision step.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Thus, choosing simpler algorithms often gives you immediate interpretability, making your life easier—no detective work needed here, just fresh ingredients!</p>

<h3 id="3-posthoc-interpretability-in-deep-learning">3. Posthoc interpretability in deep learning</h3>
<p><a id="chapter4"></a>
But what if we have sufficient samples, resources, and a strong desire to push predictive power to the limits? Deep learning is our superhero, though it usually comes wrapped in a complex, mysterious package—much like a premade smoothie. Tasty? Yes. Transparent? Not always!</p>

<p>Fortunately, we have posthoc methods to make sense of these complex models after they’ve been trained:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://papers.nips.cc/paper_files/paper/2017/hash/8a20a8621978632d76c43dfd28b67767-Abstract.html">SHAP (SHapley Additive exPlanations)</a> : SHAP assigns each feature an importance value for a particular prediction, inspired by cooperative game theory. It explains individual predictions clearly by measuring each feature’s contribution.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://proceedings.mlr.press/v70/sundararajan17a.html">Integrated Gradients</a> : Integrated gradients measure the contribution of each input feature by integrating gradients along the path from a baseline input (often zero) to the actual input. It reveals how changing each input slightly affects the model’s prediction.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>These methods act like nutritional labels or ingredient lists—turning your mysterious smoothie into something you can confidently savor!</p>

<h3 id="4-incorporation-of-biological-knowledge">4. Incorporation of biological knowledge</h3>
<p><a id="chapter5"></a>
Adding biological expertise is like sprinkling some expert seasoning that you know exactly what it does onto your dish—it elevates the entire analysis. By integrating prior biological knowledge during feature selection, we do not only narrow down the search space to “relevant features”, but also enhance interpretability by associating our features with prior biological knowledge that might boost mechanistic explaination. Resources like databases for molecular attributes and phenotype associations (e.g., KEGG, Reactome, Gene Ontology) significantly empower our interpretations.</p>

<p>However, be cautious here, biological knowledge is limited. The current available knowledge might not be sufficient to explain all the variance within our examined dataset. Always pair it with unbiased approaches to ensure comprehensive and balanced analyses.</p>

<h3 id="final-remarks">Final remarks</h3>
<p><a id="chapter6"></a>
Interpretability isn’t just icing on the ML cake—it’s the flour holding it all together. By prioritizing understandable models and cleverly combining computational methods with biological knowledge, we can unlock the true potential of ML in biomedical research.</p>

<p>Above are some thoughts for building ML models we can trust, understand, and genuinely enjoy unraveling!</p>

<p>Happy interpreting!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Interpretability in machine learning is one of the topics I paid attention to throughout my PhD. Especially in biomedical research, building models that predict outcomes accurately is thrilling, but it’s not the entire story. The magic happens when we truly understand what these models tell us and translate those insights into something meaningful. In this post, let’s dive into why interpretability matters and explore some practical ways to make our models both understandable and impactful.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Your Machine Learning Model Doesn’t Work (And How to Fix It)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/09/ml.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Your Machine Learning Model Doesn’t Work (And How to Fix It)" /><published>2025-02-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/02/09/ml</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/02/09/ml.html"><![CDATA[<p><a id="chapter1"></a>
So, you’ve built a machine learning model, but instead of making magic happen, it’s giving you garbage predictions. Before you rage-quit and blame the universe, let’s go through some common reasons why your model might be struggling—and, more importantly, how to fix them. Spoiler: it’s probably not your model’s fault. More often than not, the real issue is with your data, your approach, or both.</p>

<h3 id="1-garbage-in-garbage-out-focus-on-your-data">1. Garbage In, Garbage Out: Focus on Your Data</h3>
<p><a id="chapter2"></a>
There’s a reason it’s called <em>data</em> science. First thing you should check is your data. Your model is only as good as the data you feed it. If your input is messy, inconsistent, or just plain wrong, don’t expect miracles. Here’s what you need to check:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Normalize and transform your data</strong>: If your data has weird distributions, consider log transformations, standardization, or other normalizing techniques to make it more manageable.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Handle missing data</strong>: Don’t just pretend those NaNs don’t exist. Study the missing patterns and impute missing values wisely or, in some cases, remove problematic entries altogether.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Filter out low-quality samples</strong>: If some data points look suspicious (e.g., extreme missingness or inconsistent labels), you might need to drop them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Remove redundant variables</strong>: More features don’t always mean better models. Get rid of irrelevant or highly correlated variables.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Apply feature selection</strong>: Use methods like Recursive Feature Elimination (RFE), Lasso regression or even <a href="/projects/2.imml">my fancy IMML framework</a> to keep only the most important features.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Study batch and technical effects</strong>: If your data comes from multiple sources, batch effects can introduce bias. PCA or t-SNE can help identify these problems.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Identify outliers</strong>: Look at the distribution of your features. Box plots, histograms, and scatter plots can reveal weird anomalies.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Leverage visualization tools</strong>: Use heatmaps to check for correlation structures and Principal Component Analysis (PCA) to detect clustering or outlier issues.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>If your data is bad, even the best model in the world won’t save you. Clean it up first.</p>

<h3 id="2-overfitting-your-model-knows-too-much-and-thats-bad">2. Overfitting: Your Model Knows Too Much (And That’s Bad)</h3>
<p><a id="chapter3"></a>
Your model may seem to perform well on training data but crashes and burns on real-world data. Congratulations—you’ve overfitted. Here’s how to fix it:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Regularization</strong>: Techniques like L1 (Lasso) and L2 (Ridge) regularization help prevent excessive complexity by penalizing large weights.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Early stopping</strong>: Stop training before your model memorizes noise.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Dropout</strong>: Randomly dropping a fraction of neurons during training forces the network to generalize better.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Weight decay</strong>: A technique to reduce overfitting by modifying the update rule for gradient descent.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Simplify your architecture</strong>: If you’re using deep learning, maybe your model doesn’t need 50 layers. Sometimes, a shallower network works just fine.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The goal is to balance learning useful patterns without memorizing noise.</p>

<h3 id="3-dealing-with-class-imbalance">3. Dealing with Class Imbalance</h3>
<p><a id="chapter4"></a>
If your dataset is 90% one class and 10% another, your model might take the easy way out and just predict the majority class all the time. Here’s what you can do:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Resampling techniques</strong>: Use oversampling (e.g., SMOTE) to generate more samples of the minority class or undersampling to remove some majority class instances.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Class weighting</strong>: Modify your loss function to give more importance to the minority class.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Use different evaluation metrics</strong>: Accuracy isn’t useful when dealing with imbalanced data. Instead, use F1-score, precision-recall curves, or the area under the ROC curve (AUC-ROC).</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Ignoring class imbalance leads to models that look good on paper but fail in real-world scenarios.</p>

<h3 id="4-choosing-the-right-algorithm-and-metrics">4. Choosing the Right Algorithm and Metrics</h3>
<p><a id="chapter5"></a>
Not all algorithms are created equal. If your model is too simple, it won’t capture important patterns. If it’s too complex, it won’t generalize and be harder to interpret. You need to find the sweet spot.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Predictive power, and interpretability</strong>: A deep learning model might give you the best accuracy, but is it necessary? Simpler models like decision trees, logistic regression, or gradient boosting may work just as well while being easier to explain.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Use cross-validation</strong>: Stratified k-fold cross-validation ensures your model is tested on different portions of your dataset and prevents you from fooling yourself with lucky train-test splits.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Pick proper performance metrics</strong>: Depending on your problem, accuracy might be a terrible metric. Use precision-recall, F1-score, or mean squared error (MSE) depending on your task.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>A good model isn’t just one that works well—it’s one that works well and makes sense.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p><a id="chapter6"></a>
If your machine learning model isn’t working, don’t panic. It’s usually not the algorithm’s fault. More often than not, bad data, overfitting, class imbalance, or inappropriate model choices are to blame. By cleaning your data, preventing overfitting, handling imbalanced classes, and choosing the right metrics, you can turn things around.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, machine learning is as much about understanding your data as it is about fancy models. Get your foundations right, and your model will start making sense. Happy debugging!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[So, you’ve built a machine learning model, but instead of making magic happen, it’s giving you garbage predictions. Before you rage-quit and blame the universe, let’s go through some common reasons why your model might be struggling—and, more importantly, how to fix them. Spoiler: it’s probably not your model’s fault. More often than not, the real issue is with your data, your approach, or both.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ways to Imporove Your (Scientific) Talks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/01/25/scitalks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ways to Imporove Your (Scientific) Talks" /><published>2025-01-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/01/25/scitalks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/01/25/scitalks.html"><![CDATA[<p><a id="chapter1"></a>
Let’s face it, giving a good scientific talk is a skill that can set you apart. Whether you’re presenting at a conference, teaching a class, or keeping your team awake during a meeting, how you communicate your research matters. It’s not just about dumping data; it’s about inspiring, educating, and connecting with your audience. Based on my own (sometimes humbling and occasionally amusing) experiences during my PhD, here’s a practical guide to help you deliver scientific talks that people will actually remember.</p>

<h3 id="1-have-a-high-quality-slide-deck">1. Have a high quality slide deck</h3>
<p><a id="chapter2"></a></p>

<p>Your slides are your backup singers — they shouldn’t steal the spotlight, but they need to be on point. Here’s how to make them work for you:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Focus on figures and visuals</strong>: Use charts, graphs, and diagrams instead of dense tables or paragraphs. A clear bar graph or pie chart will always outshine a cluttered table of numbers. For example, show a colorful barplot summarizing frequencies instead of a table full of numbers. It’s quicker to digest and more engaging.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Minimize text</strong>: Less is definitely more. Keep bullet points short and stick to one idea per slide. No one wants to read a wall of text — your audience came to hear you, not read your slides. For instance, replace a paragraph with a crisp sentence or a few sharp bullet points.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Leverage animations and transitions</strong>: Animations aren’t just fun; they’re practical. Use them to reveal information step by step. If you’re showing a complex workflow, highlight one part at a time to guide your audience’s focus. Just don’t go overboard with spinning text — this isn’t a game show.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Readable text size</strong>: Make sure your text can be read without binoculars. A minimum font size of 24 points ensures legibility even for the folks at the back of the room.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Be specific</strong>: Vague slide titles like “Results” don’t cut it. Go for something descriptive, like “Fatty Acid Levels Increased Over Time.” Label axes, include units, and make sure your graphs tell a clear story. Your audience will thank you for it.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="2-start-easy">2. Start easy</h3>
<p><a id="chapter3"></a></p>

<p>Ease your audience in with something light and relatable. Think of it as the warm-up act before the main show. When you start with a familiar concept or example, you create a comfortable vibe and help your audience feel grounded. For example, if your talk is about diabetes research, begin with something everyone understands, like how sugary snacks impact blood sugar. It sets the stage for the more complex stuff and makes your audience feel included.</p>

<h3 id="3-embrace-story-telling">3. Embrace story telling</h3>
<p><a id="chapter4"></a></p>

<p>Who doesn’t love a good story? Even in science, storytelling keeps your audience hooked. Here’s how to frame your talk as a narrative:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Set the scene</strong>: Introduce the problem or question your research tackles. Make it relatable or intriguing.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Hypothesis</strong>: Explain the knowledge gap and why it’s worth exploring. Give your audience a reason to care.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Results</strong>: Share what you found, focusing on the “aha!” moments.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Conclusion</strong>: Tie everything back to your initial question and wrap it up neatly, like a Netflix season finale.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>For example, instead of saying, “We performed this experiment and found X,” try something like, “We wanted to solve this puzzle. After testing three possible explanations, here’s what we uncovered…” It’s more engaging and memorable.</p>

<h3 id="4-be-precise-and-coherent">4. Be precise and coherent</h3>
<p><a id="chapter5"></a></p>

<p>Your talk should flow logically and focus on the essentials. No one wants to play detective to figure out your main points.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Clarity</strong>: Use simple language and define technical terms. Be consistent with visuals and even your color schemes to avoid confusion.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Logical flow</strong>: Build your talk step by step, like assembling IKEA furniture (but hopefully less frustrating). Don’t make your audience connect the dots themselves.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Highlight key points</strong>: Have too many results? Pick the top ones and summarize the rest. For instance, consolidate five slides of raw data into one powerful summary slide.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="5-prepare-for-qa">5. Prepare for Q&amp;A</h3>
<p><a id="chapter6"></a></p>

<p>The Q&amp;A session is your moment to shine—or at least not panic. Here’s how to prepare:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Know your audience</strong>: Anticipate their level of expertise and tailor your answers accordingly. For non-specialists, simplify without dumbing things down.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Practice responses</strong>: Think of potential questions and rehearse answers. If you don’t know something, it’s okay to admit it and offer to follow up.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Clarify before answering</strong>: If a question is vague, ask for clarification. It’s better than guessing and going off-track.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="6-practice-practice-practice">6. Practice, practice, practice</h3>
<p><a id="chapter7"></a></p>

<p>Preparation is your best friend. The more you practice, the smoother your talk will be:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Time yourself</strong>: Stick to your allotted time. Nobody wants to miss lunch just because you couldn’t stop talking.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Record yourself</strong>: Watching a recording can be eye-opening. You might notice habits like speaking too fast or using too many filler words.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Seek feedback</strong>: Run through your talk with colleagues or friends. They’ll catch things you missed, like unclear explanations or awkward slides.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="final-remarks">Final remarks</h3>
<p><a id="chapter8"></a></p>

<p>Giving a good scientific talk takes effort, but the payoff is worth it. By creating high-quality slides, starting with relatable concepts, embracing storytelling, staying precise, and practicing thoroughly, you can transform your presentations from forgettable to fantastic. The goal isn’t just to share data—it’s to spark curiosity, inspire understanding, and maybe even leave your audience wanting more. Try out these tips for your next talk.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Let’s face it, giving a good scientific talk is a skill that can set you apart. Whether you’re presenting at a conference, teaching a class, or keeping your team awake during a meeting, how you communicate your research matters. It’s not just about dumping data; it’s about inspiring, educating, and connecting with your audience. Based on my own (sometimes humbling and occasionally amusing) experiences during my PhD, here’s a practical guide to help you deliver scientific talks that people will actually remember.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting the Most Out of Conferences (As an Introvert)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/21/conference.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting the Most Out of Conferences (As an Introvert)" /><published>2024-12-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-12-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/12/21/conference</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/21/conference.html"><![CDATA[<p><a id="chapter1"></a>
Ah, conferences—the ultimate mix of excitement, terror, and free coffee. For introverts, they can feel like stepping into a jungle of name tags and small talk. But don’t worry, with a little prep and a dash of humor, you can definitely ace this (speaking from experience). Seriously, as a proud introvert, I truly believe we have what it takes to excel in these kinds of social events. So here’s your guide to making it through without hiding under the refreshment table.</p>

<h3 id="1-gear-up-mentally-channel-your-inner-warrior">1. Gear Up Mentally: Channel Your Inner Warrior</h3>
<p><a id="chapter2"></a>
Conferences are essentially networking marathons. Before diving in, remind yourself that you can do this. Visualize yourself confidently chatting with others like the introverted rockstar you are. One thing I usually do is think about worst-case scenarios during socialization and either find solutions or mentally accept them and move on, which ultimately eases my mind. That being said, socializing is optional, so give yourself permission to step away when you need to recharge. It’s not a sprint; it’s a strategic stroll.</p>

<h3 id="2-dress-like-you-belong">2. Dress Like You Belong</h3>
<p><a id="chapter3"></a>
This may not be the most important thing, but first impressions matter, so aim for that “I’m professional but approachable” vibe. Comfortable shoes are non-negotiable because you’ll be walking a lot. And don’t forget your secret weapon—a killer outfit that says, “Yes, I’m here, and I’m fabulous.” Bonus points if it has pockets for business cards.</p>

<h3 id="3-research-the-schedule-to-avoid-fomo-like-a-pro">3. Research the Schedule to Avoid FOMO Like a Pro</h3>
<p><a id="chapter4"></a>
Bigger conferences can be overwhelming, with extensive agendas and large venues where many things happen in parallel. Before the conference, comb through the schedule and highlight talks or events that genuinely interest you. Not everything will be your cup of tea, so don’t force it. Knowing where you want to be means less wandering aimlessly and more time for meaningful experiences.</p>

<h3 id="4-master-the-art-of-small-talk-yes-you-can">4. Master the Art of Small Talk (Yes, You Can)</h3>
<p><a id="chapter5"></a>
Small talk doesn’t have to be scary—it’s just verbal appetizers. Practice a few go-to lines like, “What did you think of that last session?” or “What speakers have stood out to you so far?” Keep it light, show genuine interest, and let the conversation flow naturally. The key is to be specific enough to engage but open enough to keep the conversation going. Avoid questions that lead to dead ends.</p>

<h3 id="5-pitch-perfect-your-research-in-2-3-sentences">5. Pitch Perfect: Your Research in 2-3 Sentences</h3>
<p><a id="chapter6"></a>
You’re at a scientific conference, so you should be ready to talk about science. Besides listening to what others are working on, being able to describe your research in a stimulating way is a useful skill. Prepare a short, snappy description of your work — something even your non-academic aunt could understand. Keep it concise with a few keywords to spark interest. You never know who might be intrigued enough to ask for more details.</p>

<h3 id="6-be-a-listener-not-a-loudspeaker">6. Be a Listener, Not a Loudspeaker</h3>
<p><a id="chapter7"></a>
Whether it’s small talk or a science discussion, being a good listener goes a long way. The best communicators are those who listen well, understand, and elaborate thoughtfully. You don’t have to dominate conversations with your own stories to make an impact. Take time to listen to your colleagues, ask thoughtful questions, nod wisely, and genuinely engage. People love being heard, and you’ll stand out as someone worth talking to.</p>

<h3 id="7-social-events-coffee-breaks-and-dinners-are-the-real-mvps">7. Social Events: Coffee Breaks and Dinners Are the Real MVPs</h3>
<p><a id="chapter8"></a>
Here’s a secret: the best part of conferences often happens outside the lecture halls. Coffee breaks, happy hours, and conference dinners are prime opportunities to meet people in a relaxed setting. These are excellent playgrounds to practice the networking skills mentioned above. Plus, there’s usually food, and food makes everything better.</p>

<h3 id="8-carve-out-me-time-and-recharge">8. Carve Out ‘Me Time’ and Recharge</h3>
<p><a id="chapter9"></a>
Let’s be real—socializing can be exhausting, especially at scientific conferences. Schedule breaks for yourself to decompress, whether it’s a quiet walk, a power nap, or a guilt-free scroll through memes. These moments can help recharge your social battery and keep you feeling balanced.</p>

<h3 id="9-the-aftermath-follow-up">9. The Aftermath: Follow Up</h3>
<p><a id="chapter10"></a>
The conference doesn’t end when the lights go out. Send friendly emails or LinkedIn messages to the people you connected with. Mention something specific from your conversation to make it personal. This follow-up can turn casual connections into long-term relationships.</p>

<h3 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3>
<p>Conferences might not be every introvert’s dream, but they’re manageable—and even enjoyable—with the right mindset and strategies. Remember, you don’t have to be the loudest voice in the room to make an impression. Just be yourself (with a little planning and coffee). You’ve got this!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ah, conferences—the ultimate mix of excitement, terror, and free coffee. For introverts, they can feel like stepping into a jungle of name tags and small talk. But don’t worry, with a little prep and a dash of humor, you can definitely ace this (speaking from experience). Seriously, as a proud introvert, I truly believe we have what it takes to excel in these kinds of social events. So here’s your guide to making it through without hiding under the refreshment table.]]></summary></entry></feed>